A Guide to the Records of the Drug Policy Office of Governor Lawrence Douglas Wilder, 1987-1994 (bulk 1990-1994)
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Records of the Drug Policy Office of Governor Lawrence Douglas Wilder, 1987-1994 (bulk 1990-1994)
The Library of Virginia
35386, 35669
33.15 cu. ft. (95 boxes)
Virginia. Governor (1990-1994: Wilder)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Transferred by Governor Lawrence Douglas Wilder on 13 June 1997 (Accession 35386) and 14 January 1998 (Accession 35669). The records are filed under Accession 35386.
Biographical Information
Lawrence Douglas Wilder was born in Richmond, Va., on January 17, 1931. He graduated from Virginia Union University in 1951 and afterwards was drafted into the Army, where he served in the Korean War from 1952-1953 and received a bronze star. He then attended the Howard University School of Law and graduated in 1959. Douglas Wilder was elected to the Virginia Senate in 1969 as the first African American member since Reconstruction and served in the Senate for five terms. In 1985, he was elected to the office of Lieutenant Governor as the first African American to be elected to statewide office in Virginia. L. Douglas Wilder won the election for Governor of Virginia in 1989 and served from January 13, 1990 to January 14, 1994. He was the first African American to be elected as Governor in United States.
Governor Wilder campaigned on a promise to be the state's drug czar and lead Virginia's efforts to combat illegal drug abuse in the state. After his election Governor Wilder established a drug policy team consisting of a Special Assistant for Drug Policy, a Special Consultant for High Risk Youth, Families, and Communities, a Grants Administrator, and an Administrative Assistant. Governor Wilder replaced Mary Sue Terry with Robert A. Williams as chairman of the Governor's Council on Alcohol and Drug Abuse Problems. Bradley G. Pollack (1990-1992) and Leslie Henderson Ellis (1992-1994) served as Grants administrators and Robert B. Northern served as the Special Assistant to the Governor for Drug Policy. Governor Wilder also created a Governor's Institute on Alcohol and Other Drugs at Virginia Commonwealth University to advice the governor on drug-control policy. The Governor used the Virginia portion of the U.S. Drug-Free Schools and Communities Act of 1986 to fund grants to schools, communities, and police departments and focused on High Risk Youth, High Risk Families, and High Risk Communities.
Scope and Content
Records, 1987-1994, of the Drug Policy Office during the administration of Governor Lawrence Douglas Wilder. The collection is housed in 95 boxes and includes brochures, budgets, clippings, correspondence, financial reports, flyers, grants, grant reviews, memorandum, minutes, newsletters, photographs, progress reports, publications, reports, and other documents. The collection is arranged into two series, Series I: Correspondence and Subject Files and Series II: Grants.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series: Series I: Correspondence and Subject Files and Series II: Grant Files.
Contents List
- Series I: Correspondence and Subject Files, 1987-1994 (bulk 1990-1994)., Extent: 7.25 cu. ft. (21 boxes). (Box 1-21)
  The Correspondence and Subject Files series is housed in 21 boxes and is arranged into two (2) subseries. Subseries have been designated for: A. Correspondence and B. Subject Files. The series consists of budgets, clippings, conference programs, correspondence, financial reports, flyers, memorandum, minutes, newsletters, publications, and reports.
  - Subseries A: Correspondence, 1988-1994, 2 cu. ft. (6 boxes) (Box 1-6)
    This subseries is housed in 5 boxes and includes correspondence, budgets, clippings, memorandum, and reports. The bulk of the letters were written to and from Robert B. Northern, Special Assistant for Drug Policy, and Bradley G. Pollack and Leslie Henderson Ellis, Grant Programs Managers. Included are copies of letters sent to grant recipients awarding grants or approvals to modify grants; reports detailing grants awarded; schedules for reviewing grants; and invitations to the Governor's Conference on Alcohol and Other Drug Abuse Prevention.
    Also includes correspondence written to the Governor regarding drug use in Virginia; ideas for substance abuse programs; alternative treatments; invitations to speak; requests for information on drug policies from other Governors; anti-drug media activities; correspondence regarding tobacco abuse; questions about the various grants; commendations for DARE troopers; correspondence with various national and international organizations aimed to address the issues of alcohol and drug use; and letters of appreciation. Includes a folder of letters sent to the Governor, 1992 August-September, regarding an article printed by columnist Ann Landers about substance abuse treatment programs for prisoners.
    Also includes memorandum from the Office of the Governor regarding administrative functions such as parking, suggestions for Council members, retirements, and transfers. Also includes correspondence, 1988-1990, from Mary Sue Terry, chairman of the Governor's Council on Alcohol and Drug Abuse Problems.
    - Correspondence, 1988-1989 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, 1991 January-June (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence, 1991 July-August (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence, 1991 September-October (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence, 1991 November-December (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence, 1992 January (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence, 1992 February 3-14 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, 1992 February 18-29 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, 1992 March 4-13 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence, 1992 March 16-31 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence, 1992 April (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence, 1992 May (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence, 1992 June 1-15 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, 1992 June 16-30 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, 1992 July (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence, 1992 August (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence, Ann Landers, 1992 August-September (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence, 1992 September 1-28 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence, 1992 September 29 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence, 1992 October 5-22 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, 1992 October 23-30 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, 1992 November (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence, 1992 December (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence, 1993 January (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence, 1993 February (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence, Senate Bill 974, 1993 February-April (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence, 1993 March (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence, 1993 April (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence, 1993 May 3-19 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, 1993 May 25-28 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, 1993 June 2-11 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence, 1993 June 14-28 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence, 1993 July (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence, 1993 August (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence, 1993 September (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence, 1993 October (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, 1993 November (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, 1993 December (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence, 1994 January (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence, undated (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Subseries B: Subject Files, 1987-1994 (bulk 1990-1994)., 5.25 cu. ft. (15 boxes) (Box 7-21)
    This subseries is housed in 15 boxes and is arranged alphabetically by folder title. Includes articles, brochures, budgets, conference programs, correspondence, flyers, memorandum, minutes, needs assessment studies, publications, reports, and videos.
    Of note are the Drug Free School and Community Act (DFSCA) folders which contain financial reports, lists of grants awarded, biennial performance report on Governor's Program (1989-1991), conference program books, non-regulatory guidance for state and local programs, and U.S. Dept. of Education, General Education Provisions Act (GEPA), Data Collection forms. Also of note are several folders relating to specific grants (Children of Alcoholics, CADRE, DARE, Emergency Grants to Schools, Governor's Council, High Risk Communities, IDEA, PULSAR, Rural grants, SAP, SASA). These folders include brochures, budgets, correspondence, grant application packages, grant recommendations and reviews, lists of grants awarded, manuals, memorandum, minutes, and newsletters. Also included are flyers, minutes, and newsletters from the Governor's Alliance for a Drug-Free Virginia and the Governor's Council on Alcohol and Drug Abuse Problems,
    Included are numerous publications on alcohol and drug related issues and policies. Included are publications from the Dept. of Mental Health, Mental Retardation and Substance Abuse regarding funding sources for prevention programs; reports from the Dept. of Criminal Justice; Governor Wilder's Agenda for Virginia; Governor Wilder's Drug Control Strategy, and Governor Wilder's Task Force on Substance Abuse and Sexual Assault on College Campuses; Southeast Regional Center for Drug-Free Schools and Communities; State Council of Higher Education LINK newsletter; U.S. Dept. of Education Administrative Regulations; U.S. Dept. of Health and Human Services, The Office of Substance Abuse Prevention (OSAP) Prevention Pipeline; budget bill of Virginia; Virginia Summit on Drugs; and numerous publications from The White House President's Commission on Model State Drug Laws.
    - Alcohol and Drug Abuse Awareness Week, 1993 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Alcoholism, 1991 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Articles, 1991-1992 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Baptists, 1993 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Bill of Rights, 1992-1993 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - By Our Own Hands, 1990-1991 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Calendar, 1992-1993 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Children of Alcoholics, 1991-1992 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Citizens Forum of Hampton, 1992 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - CADRE (Commonwealth Alliance for Drug Rehabilitation and Education), 1988-1990 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - CADRE, 1991 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - CADRE, The Community CADRE Handbook, 1992 (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - CSAPP (Community Substance Abuse Prevention Program), ca. 1991 (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - Council of Governments, 1991-1992 (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - C, Miscellaneous, 1991-1992 (Box 7, Folder 15)
    - Dept. for the Aging, undated (Box 7, Folder 16)
    - Dept. of Correctional Education, Drug Infusion Curriculum Project, 1991-1992 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Dept. of Corrections, Model Comprehensive Substance Abuse Treatment Programs for Correctional Populations, Grant application (Federal), 1993 (Box 8, Folder 2-3)
    - Dept. of Criminal Justice Services, Drug Law Enforcement Formula Grants (Federal), 1990 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Dept. of Education, At-Risk Strategies, 1992 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Dept. of Education, Steroids Resource Guide, 1993 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Dept. of Education, Youth Risk Behaviors Study, 1993 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Dept. of Motor Vehicles, Drunk and Drugged Driving Prevention, 1992-1993 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Dept. of Motor Vehicles, Highway Safety Plan, 1990 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Dept. of Motor Vehicles, Highway Safety Plan, Part 1 of 2, 1992 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Dept. of Motor Vehicles, Highway Safety Plan, Part 2 of 2, 1992 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Dept. of Personnel and Training, Policies and Procedures Manual, 1993 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Dept. of Social Services, Parenting Drug Education and Prevention Program, 1992 (Box 9, Folder 3-4)
    - DARE (Drug Abuse Resistance Education), General, 1990-1992 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - DARE, The 1986/1987 DARE Program: Strengths and Weaknesses as Perceived by Recipient School Principals and Classroom Teachers, 1987 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - DFSCA (Drug Free Schools and Communities Act), General, 1989-1993 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - DFSCA, Biennial Performance Report, 1989-1991 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - DFSCA, Conference, 6th annual, 1992 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - DFSCA, Conference, 7th annual, 1993 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - DFSCA, Forms (blank), 1991-1994 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - DFSCA, GEPA (General Education Provisions Act) 406A Data Collection, 1992-1993 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - DFSCA, National Steering Committee, 1992 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - DFSCA, Non regulatory Guidance for State and Local Programs, 1990-1993 (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - DFSCA, A Study of the Drug-Free Schools and Communities Act, 1992 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - DFSCA, Title V, Drug Education, 1991 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - DFSCA, U.S. Department of Education, 1993-1994 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Employee Assistance Programs, undated (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Emergency Grants to Schools, 1991-1992 (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - Factpack, Facts About the Commonwealth of Virginia, c. 1989 (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - Governor's Alliance for A Drug-Free Virginia, Flyers, undated (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - Governor's Alliance for A Drug-Free Virginia, Newsletters, 1991-1993 (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - Governor's Award for Anti-Drug Efforts, 1991-1992 (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - Governor's Award for Anti-Drug Efforts, 1993 (Box 11, Folder 10)
    - Governor's Council on Drug and Alcohol Abuse, 1989-1991 (Box 11, Folder 11)
    - Governor's Council on Drug and Alcohol Abuse, 1992-1993 (Box 11, Folder 12)
    - Governor's Council on Drug and Alcohol Abuse, Letterhead (blank), undated (Box 11, Folder 13)
    - Governor's Youth Council, 1991-1993 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Graphic Communications, c. 1992 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - High Risk Communities, 1991 (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - High Risk Youth, 1987 (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - Institute for A Drug-Free Workplace, 1990-1992 (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - Intensified Drug Enforcement Assistance (IDEA), 1988 (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - Just Say No, International, c. 1990 (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - Letter file directions, undated (Box 12, Folder 8)
    - Livin' Large USA, 1992 (Box 12, Folder 9)
    - Mailing list, 1992 (Box 12, Folder 10)
    - Maryland, 1991 (Box 12, Folder 11)
    - Metro Richmond Coalition Against Drugs, 1991 (Box 12, Folder 12)
    - National Drug Control Strategy, 1990 (Box 12, Folder 13-14)
    - National Drug Control Strategy, 1990 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Neighborhoods in Action, The Facilitator newsletter, 1992 (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - Notes, undated (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Performance reports, Requests, 1992-1994 (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - Presidential visit, 1992 (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - Press releases, 1991 (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - Project Streamline, 1991-1994 (Box 13, Folder 7)
    - Prom Promise, 1991 (Box 13, Folder 8)
    - Publications, Council on Coordinating Prevention, Prevention Funding Information Bulletin, 1992 (Box 13, Folder 9)
    - Publications, Dept. of Criminal Justice, Drugs in Virginia, 1991 (Box 13, Folder 10)
    - Publications, Dept. of Criminal Justice, Report, 1993 (Box 13, Folder 11)
    - Publications, Dept. of Education, Six Year Technology Plan, 1989 (Box 13, Folder 12)
    - Publications, Dept. Mental Health, Mental Retardation and Substance Abuse, A Plan for Prevention Services, 1988 (Box 13, Folder 13)
    - Publications, Dept. Mental Health, Mental Retardation and Substance Abuse, Funding Sources for Prevention Programs, 1990 (Box 13, Folder 14)
    - Publications, Dept. Mental Health, Mental Retardation and Substance Abuse, Prevention Funding Information Bulletin, 1993-1994 (Box 13, Folder 15)
    - Publications, Dept. of Planning and Budget, A Study of Prevention and Early Intervention Services in Virginia, 1992 (Box 13, Folder 16)
    - Publications, Dept. of State Police, Americans for A Drug-Free America, 1988 (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Publications, Governor L. Douglas Wilder's Agenda for Virginia, 1990 (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Publications, Governor L. Douglas Wilder's Drug Control Strategy, 1991 (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - Publications, Governor's Task Force on Substance Abuse and Sexual Assault on College Campuses, 1991-1992 (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - Publications, Join Together, Who Is Really Fighting the War on Drugs?, 1992 (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - Publications, Southeast Regional Center for Drug-Free Schools and Communities, 1992 (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - Publications, State Council for Higher Education (SCHEV), Virginia Link newsletter, 1991-1992 (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - Publications, U.S. Dept. of Education, General Administrative Regulations, 1990 (Box 14, Folder 8)
    - Publications, U.S. Dept. of Education, General Administrative Regulations, 1991 (Box 14, Folder 9)
    - Publications, U.S. Dept. of Education, General Administrative Regulations, 1992 (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - Publications, U.S. Dept. of Education, Growing Up Drug Free, 1990 (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - Publications, U.S. Dept. of Health and Human Services, Alcohol and Health, 1990 (Box 15, Folder 3)
    - Publications, U.S. Dept. of Health and Human Services, Treatment Services for Adolescent Substance Abusers, 1989 (Box 15, Folder 4)
    - Publications, U.S. Dept. of Health and Human Services, The Office of Substance Abuse Prevention (OSAP) Prevention Monograph, Communicating About Alcohol and Other Drugs: Strategies for Reaching Populations At Risk, 1990 (Box 15, Folder 5)
    - Publications, U.S. Dept. of Health and Human Services, The Office of Substance Abuse Prevention (OSAP) Prevention Pipeline, 1992 (Box 15, Folder 6)
    - Publications, U.S. Dept. of Health and Human Services, The Office of Substance Abuse Prevention (OSAP) Prevention Pipeline, 1992-1993 (Box 15, Folder 7)
    - Publications, U.S. Dept. of Health and Human Services, The Office of Substance Abuse Prevention (OSAP), Prevention Plus II, 1989 (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - Publications, U.S. Dept. of Housing and Urban Development, Home Front newsletter, 1991 (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - Publications, U.S. Office of National Drug Control Policy, Federal Drug Grants to States, 1990 (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - Publications, Virginia, Budget Bill (HD 1), 1991 (Box 16, Folder 4)
    - Publications, Virginia, The Constitution of Virginia, 1988 (Box 16, Folder 5)
    - Publications, Virginia Commonwealth University, Youth Life-Styles Inventory, 1989 (Box 16, Folder 6)
    - Publications, Virginia Council on Coordinating Prevention, 1992-2000 Comprehensive Prevention Plan for Virginia, 1991 (Box 16, Folder 7)
    - Publications, Virginia Summit on Drugs, 1990 (Box 16, Folder 8)
    - Publications, Virginia Summit on Drugs II, 1992 (Box 16, Folder 9)
    - Publications, The White House, President's Commission on Model State Drug Laws, Community Mobilization, 1993 (Box 16, Folder 10)
    - Publications, The White House, President's Commission on Model State Drug Laws, Crimes Code, 1993 (Box 17, Folder 1)
    - Publications, The White House, President's Commission on Model State Drug Laws, Drug Free Families, Schools, and Workplaces, 1993 (Box 17, Folder 2)
    - Publications, The White House, President's Commission on Model State Drug Laws, Economic Remedies, 1993 (Box 17, Folder 3)
    - Publications, The White House, President's Commission on Model State Drug Laws, Executive Summary, 1993 (Box 17, Folder 4)
    - Publications, The White House, President's Commission on Model State Drug Laws, Treatment, 1993 (Box 17, Folder 5)
    - Public Service Announcements, Tax credits, 1991-1992 (Box 17, Folder 6)
    - Police, Public Educators, and Peer Counselors Utilizing the Leadership of Students At Risk (PULSAR), General, 1991-1992 (Box 17, Folder 7)
    - PULSAR, Training, 1991-1992 (Box 17, Folder 8)
    - Reclaiming A Community, undated (Box 17, Folder 9)
    - Resource materials, 1990-1992 (Box 17, Folder 10)
    - Robinson, Ronald, 1991 (Box 18, Folder 1)
    - Rural Grants, General, 1993 (Box 18, Folder 2-3)
    - Rural Grants, Communities That Care, 1993 (Box 18, Folder 4)
    - Rural Grants, Special Training, 1993 June (Box 18, Folder 5)
    - Southside Coalition, 1993 (Box 18, Folder 6)
    - State Alliance Program, 1992 (Box 18, Folder 7)
    - State Fair, 1992 (Box 18, Folder 8)
    - Student Assistance Program (SAP), General, 1991 (Box 18, Folder 9)
    - Student Assistance Program (SAP), General, 1992 (Box 18, Folder 10)
    - Student Assistance Program (SAP), General, 1993 (Box 19, Folder 1)
    - Student Assistance Program (SAP), Workshop, 1992 September-October (Box 19, Folder 2)
    - Substance Abuse and Sexual Assault on College Campuses (SASA), 1991-1992 (Box 19, Folder 3)
    - Substance Abuse and Sexual Assault on College Campuses (SASA), 1993 (Box 19, Folder 4)
    - U.S. Dept. of Education, Acts/Amendments, undated (Box 19, Folder 5)
    - U.S. Dept. of Health and Human Services, The Office of Substance Abuse Prevention (OSAP) Regional Communications Workshop, 1990 Summer (Box 19, Folder 6-7)
    - U.S. Dept. of Health and Human Services, The Office of Substance Abuse Prevention (OSAP) Regional Conference, 1990 November (Box 20, Folder 1)
    - U.S. Dept. Housing and Urban Development, Resident Initiatives Activities, 1992 (Box 20, Folder 2)
    - U.S. Dept. of the Navy, Drug Demand Reduction Task Force, 1993 (Box 20, Folder 3)
    - U.S. Treasury Dept., U.S. Savings bond campaign, 1991 (Box 20, Folder 4)
    - U.S. Senate, Report, 1990 (Box 20, Folder 5)
    - Virginia Public Education Network, undated (Box 20, Folder 6)
    - Virginia Commonwealth University (VCU), A Baseline Survey of Drug Experimentation and Use Among 5th and 6th Grade Students in the Commonwealth of Virginia, 1988 Fall (Box 20, Folder 7)
    - Virginia's First Statewide Prevention Conference, 1992 (Box 20, Folder 8)
    - Virginians Opposing Drunk Driving, 1991 (Box 20, Folder 9)
    - Virginia Union University (VUU), 1992 (Box 20, Folder 10)
    - Videos [10 VHS tapes, unreformatted] (Box 21)
      Videos submitted by schools and organizations of their projects.
- Series II: Grants, 1987-1994., Extent: 25.90 cu. ft. (74 boxes) (Box 22-94)
  The Grant series, 1987-1994, consists of 74 boxes and is arranged alphabetically by grant name or name of agency or organization that received the grant. The bulk of the collection are the grants (approved and rejected), but also included are associated materials such as agendas, brochures, correspondence, evaluations, financial reports, letters of support, memorandum, newsletters, photographs, publications, reports, and other documents.